# Malintha Fernando (Ph.D.)

## Visiting Faculty — Machine Learning, Robotics

Luddy School of Informatics, Computing and Engineering Indiana University
Bloomington, Indiana, USA, 47401
+1 (812) 955-8882

# Overview –

I am currently a full-time visiting faculty with the department of Intelligent Systems Engineering of Indiana University. I teach the Machine Learning for Signal Processing (ENGR-E511). My research focuses on designing decentralized autonomy for interacting dynamical systems to act as a cohesive under stochastic observations and communication. I study at the intersection of game theory, graph neural networks, deep multi-agent reinforcement learning, probabilistic graphical models, and motion planning.

### Education

## Indiana University, Bloomington

2017 - 2023

**Ph.D.** in Intelligent Systems Engineering **M.S.** in Intelligent Systems Engineering **Supervised by**: Prof. Martin Swany

December 15, 2023 December, 2021

Email: ccfernan@iu.edu Website: malintha.site

Github: github.com/malintha

Major: Computer Engineering

Minor: Mathematics

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

2011 - 2015

B.Sc.(Hons.) in Information Technology

December 2015

Royal College, Sri Lanka

2002 - 2010

**GCE** Advanced Level (Physical Sciences) **GCE** Ordinary Level

2010 (Top 5% Nationwide) 2007 (10 out of 10 'A' Passes)

# Work Experiences

Open Robotics Mountain View, California Summer 2019

Mentor: Tully Foote

#### **Software Engineer Intern**

**Contributions:** Designed a framework for UAV swarm control supporting trajectory optimization and receding horizon planning (RHP).

**Technologies**: Robot Operating System (ROS), PX4, IBM CPLEX, C++, MATLAB.

WSO<sub>2</sub> Colombo, Sri Lanka 2014, 2016 - 2017

Software Engineer Software Engineer Intern January 2016 - July 2017 January - June 2014

**Contributions:** Enhanced the integration of WSO<sub>2</sub> frameworks with client APIs, web services, and IOT devices.

**Open Source Committer** 

Technologies: Java, Web Services, Web Security.

Other Technologies: Python, PyTorch, Ray Reinforcement Learning Library (RLLib), Deep Graph Library (DGL).

# Teaching

Indiana University

Associate Instructor

ENGR-533: Deep Learning Systems

Fall 2022

ENGR-210: Cyber-Physical Systems

Spring 2023, 2022, 2021

ENGR-321: Advanced Cyber-Physical Systems

Fall 2021

Co-conducted lectures, designed lecture materials, assignments on linear dynamical systems simulation and control\*.

**ENGR-523:** Internet of Things

Spring 2019

**ENGR-511:** Machine Learning and Signal Processing

Fall 2018

### Publications -

Malintha Fernando, Ransalu Senanayake, Heeyoul Choi, Martin Swany, "Graph Attention Multi-Agent Fleet Autonomy for Advanced Air Mobility", *Robotics: Science and Systems, 2023.* [Paper]

**Malintha Fernando**, Ransalu Senanayake, Ariful Azad, Martin Swany, "Graphical Games for UAV Swarm Control Under Time-Varying Communication Networks", *Intelligent Aerial Robotics: From Autonomous Micro Aerial Vehicles to Sustainable Urban Air Mobility and Operations, ICRA 2022.* 

Malintha Fernando, Ransalu Senanayake, Martin Swany, "CoCo Games: Graphical Game-Theoretic Swarm Control for Communication-Aware Coverage.", *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L), March, 2022*, [Paper][Video][Project Webpage]

Malintha Fernando "Online Flocking Control of UAVs with Mean-Field Approximation.", *International Conference on Robotics and Automation, (ICRA), Xi'an, China, 2021*, [Paper][Video][Code]

Z. Chen, **M. Fernando** and L. Liu, "A Visual Feature based Obstacle Avoidance Method for Autonomous Navigation," *IEEE Applied Imagery Pattern Recognition Workshop*, 2019.

**Malintha Fernando**, and Lantao Liu. "Formation Control and Navigation of a Quadrotor Swarm." *International Conference on Unmanned Aircraft Systems (ICUAS)*, *Atlanta, Georgia, 2019*. [Video]

**Malintha Fernando**, and Lantao Liu. "Swarming of Aerial Robots with Markov Random Field Optimization", 2020, [arXiv.]

**Fernando Malintha**, Cooray A.V.S, Indeewara T.G.H, Fernando S., "Semi-supervised Learning Framework for Knowledge Extraction in Cricket Domain", *ITRU research symposium* (2015), *University of Moratuwa*, *Sri Lanka*.

# Open Source Contributions

### MavSwarm

A Lightweight, ROS-based UAV swarm simulator with low-level control, trajectory optimization, and RHP [100+ Stars on Github].

#### ROSNS3

A *Network Simulator* (NS-3) bridge for ROS to simulate wireless communication aspects of *Primary Contributor* networked robot systems [Github Link].

#### **Mozilla Firefox**

Contributed by bug fixes and feature improvements to the browser core.

Contributor, 2013-2014

<sup>\*</sup> Course materials: Github Link.

## Talks

Guest Lecture on Multi-Agent Planning and Control - Arizona State University, November 2023

Invited Talk - University of Cambridge, UK, October 2023

Invited Talk - Georgia Institute of Technology, School of Interactive Computing, Atlanta - August 2023

RSS 2023 Workshop on Multi-Agent Planning and Navigation in Challenging Environments - July 2023

IEEE International Conference on Robot & Human Interactive Communication (RO-MAN), August 2022

Invited Talk - University of Sydney, 2022 June

ICRA 2022 Workshop for Intelligent Aerial Robotics: From Autonomous Micro Aerial Vehicles to Sustainable Urban Air Mobility and Operations.

Guest Lecture on "UAV Swarm Simulation and Control", ENGR-321, Indiana University, 2021.

"Online Flocking Control of UAVs with Mean-Field Approximation" ICRA 2021 [Video].

Invited talk at Indiana University Executive AI Summit - 2020.

Guest Lecture on "Trajectory Optimization for UAVs", ENGR-599, Indiana University, 2019.

"Formation Control and Navigation of a Quadrotor Swarm" - ICUAS 2019.

## Professional Service -

#### Reviewer

International Journal of Robust and Nonlinear Control

International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)

International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems(IROS)

IEEE Transaction on Robotics (T-RO)

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

International Symposium on Multi-Robot and Multi-Agent Systems (MRS)

Learning for Control and Dynamics Conference (L4DC)

#### Mentor

#### Undergraduate Research Opportunities in Computing (UROC) Program

Zach Seliger - Trajectory Generation and Control of a Crazyflie Drone

Ben Siefers - Neural Network based Autonomous UAV Navigation	2020
Eric Tatman - Simulating UAV Swarm Dynamics	2020

# Volunteering and Leadership ———

2018

IEEE Region 4 (Midwest) Student Activity Committee (SAC)

**Responsibilities**: Evaluating regional student activity award applications.

2019

IEEE Region 10 (Asia/Pacific) Student Activity Committee (SAC)

Responsibilities: Evaluating regional student branch activity proposals and allocate funds.

2016

**IEEE Sri Lanka Section Executive Committee** 

Responsibilities: Coordinating the activities of student branches,

Promoting IEEE activities in Sri Lankan universities.

2015/16

*Highlights:* Membership numbers increased by 30% during my tenure.

IEEE Region 10 Student/Young Professional/Women in Engineering Congress

Core Organizer, 2015

Section Student Representative

**Responsibilities**: Leading the promotional activities team.

*Highlights:* The congress attracted 200+ foreign student delegates across the region.

**IEEE University of Moratuwa Student Branch** 

Highlights: The student branch won two IEEE Darrel Chong Awards.

Vice Chair, 2013/14

Awards -

Luddy Travel Fellowship, Indiana University

2022, 2023

Graduate Student Fellowship, Indiana University

2017 - 2022

United Nations Development Program (UNDP) Hackathon - Sri Lanka

2016, Second Place

Google Summer of Code

For contributing to Mozilla Thunderbird's Calendar protocol for updating it to the latest RFC

2014, Mozilla

standards.

Institute of Engineers - Sri Lanka (IESL) Hackathon

2014, First Place

State Literary Competition (2009), Sri Lanka, Short Stories Division

2009, Finalist

### References -

Prof. Martin Swany
Chair, Dept. Intelligent Systems Engineering
Indiana University
Bloomington, IN, 47401
swany@indiana.edu

Prof. Ransalu Senanayake Dept. Computer Science Arizona State University Tempe, AZ ransalu@asu.edu

Prof. Minje Kim
Dept. Intelligent Systems Engineering
Indiana University
Bloomington, IN, 47401
minje@indiana.edu